<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<aiml>
<!--Default reply-->
<category>
    <pattern>*</pattern>
    <template>My brain can not process your input please follow the instructions:<br/>
    You can start by typing teacher or student.
    </template>
</category>
<!-- TEACHER STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>TEACHER</pattern>
    <template>
        HOW MAY I HELP YOU?
        <br/>Valid: Lesson plan
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        WHICH GROUP OF STUDENT?<br/>
        Valid:<br/>
        *KINDERGARTEN LESSON PLAN<br/>
        *STANDARD 1 LESSON PLAN<br/>
        *STANDARD 2 LESSON PLAN<br/>
        *STANDARD 3 LESSON PLAN<br/>
        *STANDARD 4 LESSON PLAN<br/>
        *STANDARD 5 LESSON PLAN
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>KINDERGARTEN LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        Kindergarten English Language Lesson Plans<br/>
        Valid:<br/>
        *Beginning Sound Match<br/>
        *Fairy Tale<br/>
        *How to Take Care of Our Oceans<br/>
        *Learning About Adjectives<br/>
        *Rainbow Fish<br/>
        *Rhyme Time<br/>
        *Rhyming Words<br/>
        *Story Sequencing<br/>
        *Tearing Into Vocabulary<br/>
        *What is a Verb
    </template>
</category>
<category>
 <pattern>BEGINNING SOUND MATCH</pattern>
  <template>
    Opening to Lesson
	Begin by asking students who in the room can spell their name.
	All students should be well versed in this after the first month or so of kindergarten.
	Ask a few students if they will spell their name out loud.
	“Brian, can you spell your name? Good now let’s take it apart. What sound does the B make? Good, now the R?...”
	Continue through at least three names so students understand that each letter makes a separate sound.
Body of Lesson
	Demonstrate to students how they will turn  a piece of construction paper lengthwise and write their name one letter at a time with enough space to glue a picture beside the letter.
	Tell students they will choose the pictures to make their letter sounds, each one will be different from other students.
	Allow students to color their chosen pictures and glue them in the appropriate spot.
	(Help struggling students get started by limiting choices if needed)
Closing
Have students share their pictures with the class by saying the sound and pictures that match. Display name art.
  </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>FAIRY TALE</pattern>
    <template>
    Opening to Lesson
	Connect to prior knowledge by reviewing real and make-believe characters
	Show students ten pictures of different characters from stories we have read in the class.  We will play a quick game of "Real or Make-Believe"
Body of Lesson
Guided Practice
	Make a KWL chart about fairy tales.
	Introduce the main elements of a fairy tale (fantasy story, has magic or spells, animals act like humans, once upon a time, good guys vs. bad guys, princes, princesses).
	Read the entire story, "The Three Little Pigs".
	To check for understanding, use name cards to randomly call on students to provide characteristics from fairy tale stories.
	Is this story a fairy tale?  Why? Students will give reasons to support.
	Dictate comments onto a chart on the board. This will be a great way to model language and check for understanding.
Independent Practice
	Strategically pair up students (varied  skill levels).
	Students will be asked to draw a picture of a part of the story that is related to being a fairy tale.
	Advanced students could extend by writing words to describe their drawing.
	Monitor comprehension by observing the conversations and drawings. Provide immediate feedback through teacher modeling.
Closing
	Students can share their findings with the class.
	This will give an opportunity for students to teach their peers.  Students will be invited to "pick" the presenter's brain by asking questions.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>How to Take Care of Our Oceans</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
I will ask the students to think of the animals learned in previous lesson and ask them where the animals live.  We will then discuss if the animals would like garbage in their homes.  I will then read the poem The Sea's in a Slump.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
After coming to the conclusion that it is important to take care of the ocean, I will then ask the students to brainstorm ways we can take care of the ocean.  If they are having trouble thinking of ideas I will guide them towards some others, but focusing mainly on pollution.
Independent Practice
After we have a list, I will tell the students that we are going to make a how-to book about caring for the ocean.  I will then tell the students to pick one of the ways and have them draw and color a picture illustrating it.  I will then ask the students to write, as best as they can, what their picture is illustrating underneath it.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>LEARNING ABOUT ADJECTIVES</pattern>
    <template>Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class if they know the story of the Three Little Pigs (the teacher can choose whichever story he/she likes).
	Tell students that it is your favorite story and ask them to listen respectfully for those who don’t know it yet. Ask them to look at the pictures and drawings as you read them the story of the Three Little Pigs.
	After reading the story, ask them which pig they like and dislike in the story.
	Ask them why they like and dislike the pig which they answered.
	As they tell you their reasons, write down all the adjectives that you hear in their answers. You can write the adjectives on to the board.
	Tell students that any word that describes things we like or dislike are called adjectives.
Body of Lesson
Guided Practice
	Invite some students to act out their favorite characters from the story then ask the class to describe characters they portrayed. Remind them that the words they are using to describe are called adjectives.
Independent Practice
	The students will be asked to write or draw at least two adjectives for every person, thing, place, or animal the teachers tells them. They must write it on their paper. If some students have trouble spelling, write some adjectives on the board.
Closing
	Ask the class to tell you what they learned about adjectives.
	Ask them the best adjectives that they can give for their parents, family, and friends.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>RAINBOW FISH</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Show the students the Rainbow Fish Book and walk through the book with them asking for predictions as you show the images and share the title etc.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Watch the Rainbow Fish video and discuss with the students whether or not Rainbow Fish was a good friend and what parts of the video showed it.
Independent Practice
After the video I will then tell the students that they are going to make their own Rainbow Fish.  I will give them the following instructions: First, put your name on the back in the middle. Next, glue your scales onto your fish.  Then color you fish’s head, fin, and tail.  Finally, cut out your fish.
Closing
Hang the fish around the classroom and discuss the importance of being a good friend and maybe discuss examples of when students have been a good friend to others or others to them.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>RHYME TIME</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by telling students that you are going to work on rhyming words. Explain that rhyming words tend to have the same letters at the end. Ask students if they can think of any words that rhyme. Tell students you are going to share a book that has lots of rhyming words. Share ‘ The Cat in the Hat’ pointing out rhyming pairs as you go.
Body of Lesson
	Have students sit with plenty of room to cut. Give students one sheet of paper (see sample) and cut along the lines as shown. Younger children may benefit from having this completed for them. Also offer students one strip per word family you are using. (Three are shown below but more or fewer can be accommodated based on your students.) Have students write letters appropriate to the word families on each strip using three fingers between each for spacing. Sample strips are provided and can be copied if needed.
	Demonstrate how to thread the strip through the cuts with the letters showing on top. (See sample)
	Allow students to thread the strip into the slats that have been cut and read each word as the strip is pulled through. Remind students that each of the words in the family rhyme. After each student reads a few words, move on to the next. If a student is struggling offer help in sounding out the initial sound and ending, with a reminder that only the initial sound is changing. Struggling students may benefit from watching the first strip being read on an overhead.
Closing
Once all students have had a chance to read a few rhyming words, have students choose at least two words from a single family and draw pictures to illustrate that rhyming word pair.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Rhyming Words</pattern>
    <template>Objectives AND Outcomes
Students will be able to identify and produce rhyming words.
Materials Needed
	crayons
	pencils
	erasers
	"Cat in the Hat" DVD and book - Get them here
	Rhyming worksheet (attached)
Procedure
Opening to Lesson
Teacher can walk into the class speaking in sentences that rhyme. The peculiar and animated way of speaking will prompt students' curiosities. As a result, students will be engaged and ask questions during this rhyming lesson. Teacher will introduce the word "rhyme" and define it as words that end with the same sounds.
Body of Lesson
	Students will watch the "Cat in the Hat" DVD.  This will link to students' background knowledge, as most of them should have seen Dr. Seuss text in the libraries.
	 As a class, discuss that rhyming words are all around us. Revisit the definition of rhyme during the lesson.
	Make a chart on butcher paper to demonstrate examples of words that rhyme.  Elicit student contributions. *For students who have difficulty remaining focused, facilitate a lot of student responses.
	Use a randomized system of name calling to help those students stay engaged. *For students with visual and spatial difficulties, I will have students point to the rhyming words. We will use colored markers to match the pairs of words that rhyme. This will provide colored contrasts for students with visual impairments.
Modeling
	Read the "Cat in the Hat" book emphasizing rhyming words. Students will clap they hear rhyming words. *Make sure to follow along with your finger so students can have a reference point. Use hand gestures, and expressions to convey important words and meanings during the rhyming lesson.
Checking for Understanding/Guided Practice
	On the rug, lead the class to complete the lyrics to a silly rhyming poem.  For example: The goat wore a ______  and sat next to the fox with _______".  Continue creating silly rhyming phrases until each student has had a turn. will use a different color marker to write the rhyming words.
Independent Practice
	Teacher can use one of the attached worksheets to allow an opportunity for students to practice independently.
Closing
	In closing the rhyming lesson, gather back on the rug to review what students took away from the lesson.
	Teacher can shout out words and ask kids to should back rhyming words.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Story Sequencing</pattern>
    <template>Opening to Lesson
	To introduce the sequencing lesson and gain students' attention, the teacher can tell a silly "out-of-order" story about his/her day. For example : "This morning, I woke up and ate dinner. Then, I put my pajamas on and went to school. Next , I brushed my teeth played with my friends".
	This can lead into a conversation about the importance of putting events in order.
	Introduce the concept of sequencing.
Body of Lesson
Modeling
	Read the focus story, "The Gingerbread Man".
	After reading the story, bring out a large poster that already has the words first, second, next, then, and last written on it.  The words are ordered like a train.  There will be an arrow starting at first and pointing to last.
	Use the pre-made story/picture cards to sequence the events in the story.
	To check for understanding, you can intentionally place some cards in the incorrect place to see if students are following along.
	You can use gestures and body language to help convey the words.
	You can use slower speech with physical cues and clear articulation when approaching key topics.
Guided Practice
	Students will be divided students into  5 groups.
	Each group will be given an event from the story  to illustrate.   They will work together to delegate responsibilities and roles.
	After the students illustrate their scene, we will gather together on the rug.
	Students will put the events in order.
	They will use a  bold marker to add the words first, second, next, then, and last to each drawing.
	As a class, we will go over their work, as we order the events  by using the sequencing words (first, second, next, then, last).
Independent Practice
	Students will work independently to sequence the events from "The Three Little Pigs".
	Students can draw the sequence of events in the story.
Closing
As a closure, students can act out the story using sequencing cues from the teacher.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>TEARING INTO VOCABULARY</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
*This activity can be used with vocabulary from any subject area.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>WHAT IS A VERB</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class to sing the birthday song.
	Encourage them to talk about how they celebrate their birthday.
	This should be an introduction to tell about action words or Verbs. The purpose is not just to introduce Verbs but to help the children understand that birthdays are special days so we celebrate the days that someone is born.
Body of Lesson
	Remind students that verbs are action words.
	Show the students the procedure of how to wrap a gift using different verbs. Students should be wrapping a box at their desk as teacher models.
	Next, have each student switch wrapped boxes with a partner. All must be able to have a box.
	Now ask them to imagine what they wish is inside their wrapped box. What can it do for them?
	Request them to make sentences that use verbs to tell how the gift they imagine can be useful for them.
	Do the optional activity if desired. (Modification and Differentiation)
Closing
	As a class, discuss many of the verbs that were used in the activity today. Write verbs on the board or on to chart paper.
	Ask them what will they do on their next birthday.
    </template>
</category>
<!-- kINDERGERTIN ENDS-->
<!-- STANDARD 1 STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>STANDARD 1 LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        1st Grade English Language Lesson Plans
        *Beginning Sound Match 1
        *Fairy Tale 1
        *Learning About Adjectives 1
        *Rhyme Time 1
        *Story Sequencing 1
        *Story Themes 1
        *Tearing Into Vocabulary 1
        *What is a Verb 1
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Beginning Sound Match 1</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Begin by asking students who in the room can spell their name.
	All students should be well versed in this after the first month or so of kindergarten.
	Ask a few students if they will spell their name out loud.
	“Brian, can you spell your name? Good now let’s take it apart. What sound does the B make? Good, now the R?...”
	Continue through at least three names so students understand that each letter makes a separate sound.
Body of Lesson
	Demonstrate to students how they will turn  a piece of construction paper lengthwise and write their name one letter at a time with enough space to glue a picture beside the letter.
	Tell students they will choose the pictures to make their letter sounds, each one will be different from other students.
	Allow students to color their chosen pictures and glue them in the appropriate spot.
	(Help struggling students get started by limiting choices if needed)
Closing
Have students share their pictures with the class by saying the sound and pictures that match. Display name art.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Fairy Tale 1</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Connect to prior knowledge by reviewing real and make-believe characters
	Show students ten pictures of different characters from stories we have read in the class.  We will play a quick game of "Real or Make-Believe"
Body of Lesson
Guided Practice
	Make a KWL chart about fairy tales.
	Introduce the main elements of a fairy tale (fantasy story, has magic or spells, animals act like humans, once upon a time, good guys vs. bad guys, princes, princesses).
	Read the entire story, "The Three Little Pigs".
	To check for understanding, use name cards to randomly call on students to provide characteristics from fairy tale stories.
	Is this story a fairy tale?  Why? Students will give reasons to support.
	Dictate comments onto a chart on the board. This will be a great way to model language and check for understanding.
Independent Practice
	Strategically pair up students (varied  skill levels).
	Students will be asked to draw a picture of a part of the story that is related to being a fairy tale.
	Advanced students could extend by writing words to describe their drawing.
	Monitor comprehension by observing the conversations and drawings. Provide immediate feedback through teacher modeling.
Closing
	Students can share their findings with the class.
	This will give an opportunity for students to teach their peers.  Students will be invited to "pick" the presenter's brain by asking questions.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Learning About Adjectives 1</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class if they know the story of the Three Little Pigs (the teacher can choose whichever story he/she likes).
	Tell students that it is your favorite story and ask them to listen respectfully for those who don’t know it yet. Ask them to look at the pictures and drawings as you read them the story of the Three Little Pigs.
	After reading the story, ask them which pig they like and dislike in the story.
	Ask them why they like and dislike the pig which they answered.
	As they tell you their reasons, write down all the adjectives that you hear in their answers. You can write the adjectives on to the board.
	Tell students that any word that describes things we like or dislike are called adjectives.
Body of Lesson
Guided Practice
	Invite some students to act out their favorite characters from the story then ask the class to describe characters they portrayed. Remind them that the words they are using to describe are called adjectives.
Independent Practice
	The students will be asked to write or draw at least two adjectives for every person, thing, place, or animal the teachers tells them. They must write it on their paper. If some students have trouble spelling, write some adjectives on the board.
Closing
	Ask the class to tell you what they learned about adjectives.
	Ask them the best adjectives that they can give for their parents, family, and friends.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Rhyme Time 1</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by telling students that you are going to work on rhyming words. Explain that rhyming words tend to have the same letters at the end. Ask students if they can think of any words that rhyme. Tell students you are going to share a book that has lots of rhyming words. Share ‘ The Cat in the Hat’ pointing out rhyming pairs as you go.
Body of Lesson
	Have students sit with plenty of room to cut. Give students one sheet of paper (see sample) and cut along the lines as shown. Younger children may benefit from having this completed for them. Also offer students one strip per word family you are using. (Three are shown below but more or fewer can be accommodated based on your students.) Have students write letters appropriate to the word families on each strip using three fingers between each for spacing. Sample strips are provided and can be copied if needed.
	Demonstrate how to thread the strip through the cuts with the letters showing on top. (See sample)
	Allow students to thread the strip into the slats that have been cut and read each word as the strip is pulled through. Remind students that each of the words in the family rhyme. After each student reads a few words, move on to the next. If a student is struggling offer help in sounding out the initial sound and ending, with a reminder that only the initial sound is changing. Struggling students may benefit from watching the first strip being read on an overhead.
Closing
Once all students have had a chance to read a few rhyming words, have students choose at least two words from a single family and draw pictures to illustrate that rhyming word pair.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Story Sequencing 1</pattern>
    <template>
Opening to Lesson
	To introduce the sequencing lesson and gain students' attention, the teacher can tell a silly "out-of-order" story about his/her day. For example : "This morning, I woke up and ate dinner. Then, I put my pajamas on and went to school. Next , I brushed my teeth played with my friends".
	This can lead into a conversation about the importance of putting events in order.
	Introduce the concept of sequencing.
Body of Lesson
Modeling
	Read the focus story, "The Gingerbread Man".
	After reading the story, bring out a large poster that already has the words first, second, next, then, and last written on it.  The words are ordered like a train.  There will be an arrow starting at first and pointing to last.
	Use the pre-made story/picture cards to sequence the events in the story.
	To check for understanding, you can intentionally place some cards in the incorrect place to see if students are following along.
	You can use gestures and body language to help convey the words.
	You can use slower speech with physical cues and clear articulation when approaching key topics.
Guided Practice
	Students will be divided students into  5 groups.
	Each group will be given an event from the story  to illustrate.   They will work together to delegate responsibilities and roles.
	After the students illustrate their scene, we will gather together on the rug.
	Students will put the events in order.
	They will use a  bold marker to add the words first, second, next, then, and last to each drawing.
	As a class, we will go over their work, as we order the events  by using the sequencing words (first, second, next, then, last).
Independent Practice
	Students will work independently to sequence the events from "The Three Little Pigs".
	Students can draw the sequence of events in the story.
Closing
As a closure, students can act out the story using sequencing cues from the teacher.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Story Themes 1</pattern>
    <template>
Opening to Lesson
Pre-Reading and making predictions: Look through the cover, illustrations, title, table of contents etc. Talk about the idea of a club and brainstorm ideas of clubs students are in, or know about or want to make. (CFU: Listen and write different types of clubs as students tell you. Continuously challenge and ask follow-up questions as you add to the board bubble map.)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Read The Only One Club aloud to the class. (CFU: Check for understanding after every idea or step, continuously ask to clarify vocabulary or repeat words throughout reading.)
Guided Practice 1
Teach descriptive qualities and character traits by writing traits about myself on the board. Ask students what I am doing and aid them to the answer of “describing myself” or “writing traits about me. Have students read the listed descriptions and decide as a class which ones make me ‘unique’ and eligible for ‘the only one club.’ (CFU: continuously aid students to the correct answers, while challenging them to think further and more in depth about each description I have written about myself.)
Guided Practice 2
Review the simple idea of uniqueness. “I’m the only one wearing heels… so that makes me unique! I am the only one who has lived in Czech Republic… so that also makes me unique!” Give students a small piece of paper, and have them create a sentence about themselves to describe their uniqueness. Then have students write one thing about themselves they feel is different from others in the class. Have the students crumple it up, stand in a large circle around the classroom and have student throw it to the center box I placed. (CFU: rotate around the class as I answer questions, help students brainstorm ideas, or assist in writing their sentence.)
Independent Practice
Have students go to the center of the classroom and choose a ‘snowball’ of crumpled paper.  Then have students work independently and create a badge for their classmates with what was written on their chosen ‘snowball.’
Closing
Choose students at random to present their badges, and either have students guess who it belongs to, or simple have students stand and accept their new badge when it is presented by their classmate.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Tearing Into Vocabulary 1</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
*This activity can be used with vocabulary from any subject area.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>What is a Verb 1</pattern>
    <template>
    Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class to sing the birthday song.
	Encourage them to talk about how they celebrate their birthday.
	This should be an introduction to tell about action words or Verbs. The purpose is not just to introduce Verbs but to help the children understand that birthdays are special days so we celebrate the days that someone is born.
Body of Lesson
	Remind students that verbs are action words.
	Show the students the procedure of how to wrap a gift using different verbs. Students should be wrapping a box at their desk as teacher models.
	Next, have each student switch wrapped boxes with a partner. All must be able to have a box.
	Now ask them to imagine what they wish is inside their wrapped box. What can it do for them?
	Request them to make sentences that use verbs to tell how the gift they imagine can be useful for them.
	Do the optional activity if desired. (Modification and Differentiation)
Closing
	As a class, discuss many of the verbs that were used in the activity today. Write verbs on the board or on to chart paper.
	Ask them what will they do on their next birthday.
</template>
</category>
<!-- STANDARD 1 ENDS-->
<!-- STANDARD 2 STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>STANDARD 2 LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        2nd Grade English Language Lesson Plans
        *Authors Purpose 2
        *Discovering Adjectives 2
        *Good Deeds 2
        *Main Idea and Details 2
        *Hiding Homophones 2
        *Learning About Adjectives 2
        *Main Idea 2
        *Moody Reading 2
        *Rhyme Time 2
        *Story Themes 2
        *Tearing Into Vocabulary 2
        *What is a Verb 2
        *Writing Main Idea 2
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>AUTHORS PURPOSE 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will gain students' attention by playing a familiar/popular song (age appropriate).
	Teacher can ask students to listen to the lyrics.
	Students will then talk in groups to try to figure out the meaning/main idea of the song.
Body of Lesson
	As a class, read “Frog and Toad are Friends” by Arnold Lobel.
	In a circle on the rug,  review the meaning of “author’s message”.
	Students will brainstorm with the person next to them in order to create an answer to the following question: “Why do you think we need to spend time thinking about the author’s purpose?”
	Students will share their responses.
Guided/Independent Practice
	Students will work in groups to fill out the graphic organizer chart.
	Why did the author write this story?How do you know?
	Each group will present their findings to the rest of the class.
Closing
	Each student will receive one post-it.
	On the post-it, students will work independently to answer the following question: “Why do you think it is important to think about the author’s purpose?”
	At the end of the lesson, students will stick their post-its to the board or a pre-made chart. The chart can simply be made from butcher paper.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Discovering Adjectives 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the students what an Adjective is and write their definition on the board. (A describing word).
	Ask students what their favorite adjectives are and make a list of as many as they can think of on the board.
	Delicious, fun, pretty, smart, happy, sad, angry, rich, red, green, blue, cold, hot, sweet….
Body of Lesson
Modeling
	The teacher shows the students a bundle of grapes and asks how many students have eaten grapes before. Probably all of the students have.
	Now ask students what adjectives listed on the board could describe the look of the grapes.
	Add words to the list as students shout them out: green, purple, round, small, oval, smooth, pretty, weird…
	Now give a few students a grape and ask them what the grape physically feels like to the touch: cold, round, wet, sticky…
	Smell the grapes and instruct students to do the same, add more adjectives to the board: fruity, sweet,…
	Now eat one of the grapes and tell the students “Mmmm, delicious, sweet, a little sour, juicy, etc…” Let some students eat the grapes and add more adjectives to the list.
	Now ask those students how they feel after eating the grapes: hungry, happy, satisfied…
	Now ask the students who didn’t participate how they feel: hungry, sad…
	Give the rest of the students a grape.
Guided Practice
	Divide students into groups of 4.
	Give each student a worksheet.
	Pass out 4 identical objects to each group (1 group receives 4 apples, group 2 recieves 4 juice boxes, etc…)
	Instruct students to wait for your instructions as they work in their groups.
	In groups, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Look.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Touch.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Smell.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Taste.
	Finally, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Feel (emotional)
	Depending on time, you can give students an additional worksheet and repeat the assignment with another food object.
Independent Practice
	As independent practice, students will write a summary of the days activity, using their favorite adjectives.
	Ex. Today in class I worked with my group to describe an apple. First, we just looked at the apple, it was round, red and inviting. Next, we touched the cool, smooth apple and thought of more adjectives to describe it. Then, we ate the apple. It was delicious, juicy and sweet. Finally we described how eating the apple made me feel. It made me feel happy and satisfied, but also ready for lunch! All in all, it was a fantastic activity.
Closing
Have students read their summaries aloud. Encourage students to repeat the activity at home with their family, commenting on the colors and tastes of their dinner.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Good Deeds 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will preface the lesson with a discussion on the importance of Dr. Seuss. The teacher will ask the students for the names of their favorite Dr. Seuss books. The teacher will ask the students if they notice anything about what the books have in common.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will have students gather on the rug to listen to a “read aloud” of Horton Hears a Who by Dr. Seuss. The teacher will prompt the students to put their listening ears on. Throughout the story the teacher will prompt the students to participate in the reading by having them complete each line with the correct rhyming word.
Guided Practice 1
After the story is read the teacher will lead a discussion on the lesson of the story with the students that, “a person’s a person no matter how small.” Some questions that will be asked are: What did Horton do that was so important? How do you think it made the Who’s feel that Horton cared so much? What would have happened to the Who’s if Horton didn’t protect them? What was the lesson of this story? What does, “ a person’s a person no matter how small” mean? Have you ever done a good deed for someone else? How did it make them feel? How did it make you feel? The teacher will get various responses from students.
Independent Practice
The teacher will have the students return to their desks. The teacher will then explain that the students will be making a clover. The students will be drawing a picture of a nice thing that they did for someone else. On the lines provided, the students will write one sentence that says what they did and another sentence that describes how it made them feel.
Closing
Have students present their clovers to the class or in pairs.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Main Idea and Details 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Have students close their eyes and use their ears to listen to these sounds. Think about what these sounds are, what’s making them, or who is making them. “Don’t answer out loud, you will share with your partner in a second”
	Play bee sounds then think-pair-share with your partner, “I think these sounds are made by...” Call on students to answer. Sentence frame: “my partner/friend said..”
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Using the projector to show the book to all the students.
Show book to students, do a PICTURE WALK with them through the book. Ask students to predict what they think the book will be about. Read the first two pages of the book, stop and ask question to students, “Has your prediction changed? what do you predict we will learn about the main character?”
Guided Practice 1
Call up helpers to use pointer to allow students to follow along with the words as students continue to read the story. Pause to ask questions to the students and have answers prewritten but covered on graphic organizer:
What is the setting of the story?
what insects make honey?
Where do bees get the nectar that they bring back to their houses/hives?
What does the honey from Fred’s bee’s taste like?
Guided Practice 2
After the book is read, one student will come up to the front of the class and sit in the “HOT SEAT”; this student will take on the personality traits of one of the characters in the story (The bees, or Fred) and other students will take turns asking the HOT SEAT student questions pertaining to the books. The teacher will start with an example: “Mr. Bee, where do you live?” Student will respond as if he was the bee from the book. The student in HOT SEAT will then call on other students that are raising their hands to ask him/her questions.
Independent Practice
Evidence based writing: have students write their answer to the question: “Why does Fred make honey?” and support your answer with evidence from the story. Students will write 1-paragraph f students have time, they may draw a picture to represent what they wrote. (If students have time, they may draw a picture to represent what they wrote.)
Closing
Have students share their answers orally; review writing samples that are turned in.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Hiding Homophones 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Offer students the following bit of information: English is one of the hardest languages in the world to learn. Ask students if they can guess why it is so hard. Encourage answers by displaying the following sentences: They’re going to their car that is over there.; He blew the blue horn two too many times.;  The flower made out of flour and water won number one in the contest. Explain that the words that sound the same are homophones and such words make English very difficult to learn, but that today you are going to create a ‘cheat sheet’ for some common homophones.
Body of Lesson
	Before providing a list of homophones, have students see if they can come up with some on their own. List these on the board or overhead. If there are no suggestions choose words appropriate for the grade level and ability level of the students.
	Review words and meanings with students before passing out paper. Fold the paper into fourths as shown below. Cut tabs on either side (shown below) to create flaps for each homophone pair. Have students list the pairs on the outside of the flap, across from each other. Under each flap draw a simple picture to illustrate the word. This is now a ‘cheat sheet’ for homophones. You can allow students to choose a set number of pairs or give them the words you feel are best. If time permits allow students to decorate the back.
Closing
Have students share their illustrations with a partner and then allow a few students to share which pair of homophones is the hardest for them to remember. Use the foldable in other assignments as a ‘cheat sheet’ when possible.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Learning About Adjectives 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class if they know the story of the Three Little Pigs (the teacher can choose whichever story he/she likes).
	Tell students that it is your favorite story and ask them to listen respectfully for those who don’t know it yet. Ask them to look at the pictures and drawings as you read them the story of the Three Little Pigs.
	After reading the story, ask them which pig they like and dislike in the story.
	Ask them why they like and dislike the pig which they answered.
	As they tell you their reasons, write down all the adjectives that you hear in their answers. You can write the adjectives on to the board.
	Tell students that any word that describes things we like or dislike are called adjectives.
Body of Lesson
Guided Practice
	Invite some students to act out their favorite characters from the story then ask the class to describe characters they portrayed. Remind them that the words they are using to describe are called adjectives.
Independent Practice
	The students will be asked to write or draw at least two adjectives for every person, thing, place, or animal the teachers tells them. They must write it on their paper. If some students have trouble spelling, write some adjectives on the board.
Closing
	Ask the class to tell you what they learned about adjectives.
	Ask them the best adjectives that they can give for their parents, family, and friends.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Main Idea 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will activate prior knowledge and connect the content to the students by asking, “what are things you do at recess?” As students brainstorm ideas aloud, the teacher will write their answers into a large bubble map outlined on the board.
The teacher will connect this content to the new information they will learn today by explaining, “Students, you’ve just listed many details that support our topic “Things we do at recess.” A topic is used to create a sentence that tells what a paragraph is about. We call this sentence the main idea. Today, we will identify main ideas and supporting details.”
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will promote the concept development by explicitly stating “the main idea is the one idea that the passage is mostly about. A supporting detail explains, or tells more about, the main idea.”
Guided Practice 1
The teacher will then show a short 1 minute video on a computer, tablet or television that uses singing and rhyming to explain examples of the main idea and supporting details in a creative way. The teacher will ask the students questions about the story in the video. “What was the main idea, what was a detail that supported the main idea?” The teacher will then provide the students with a printed copy of the lyrics. The teacher will ask the class to read the short rhyming lyrics together as a class. The teacher will play the video one more time, asking the students to sing along.
Independent Practice
The teacher will give each student one worksheet of 6 different variations. The teacher will promote skill development by asking the students to silently read the passage, to circle the main idea and underline the supporting details of the passage.
Closing
The teacher will ask select students to state their answers following the prompt: “The main idea is …” and “One supporting detail is…”
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Moody Reading 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Begin by telling students you are going to read them the same page of a book twice.
	Ask them to quietly listen as you read the same thing and then tell them you would like to discuss the readings.
	The first time you read the page (text of your choice), read in a monotone voice with no feeling at all.
	Reread the passage with emotion and feeling. Ask students what was different about the two readings.
	If students do not respond of hear the difference, guide the discussion to how reading with emotion and feeling can make a passage more interesting and hold the listeners attention.
Body of Lesson
	Tell students that they are going to practice reading with emotion. Remind them that the words are not what is important, it is the emotion they are reading with at the time. Hand out one colored strip or paper to each student; make sure a variety is handed out.
	On the board or overhead white each color that was handed out and assign it an emotion. (Samples shown) Demonstrate how to read the following line in each emotion (or your chosen emotions) “The dog jumped over the fence”.
	Allow students to take turns reading in their given ‘emotion’. The goal is not to read the words as you would if you were simply trying to understand the story, but to express an emotion while reading to understand how much more interesting this can make reading.
	*If students enjoy this activity and you want a challenge, use the colors to represent a group of people so students would read as a teacher/motivational speaker/wrestler/coach/etc. This is fun and a bit more challenging.
Closing
After everyone has had a chance to read, allow students to break into small groups of three or four. Have students choose two colors each and read through an entire text, taking turns reading in their ‘emotion’. Encourage students to read with appropriate emotions during other activities.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Rhyme Time 2</pattern>
    <template>
Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by telling students that you are going to work on rhyming words. Explain that rhyming words tend to have the same letters at the end. Ask students if they can think of any words that rhyme. Tell students you are going to share a book that has lots of rhyming words. Share ‘ The Cat in the Hat’ pointing out rhyming pairs as you go.
Body of Lesson
	Have students sit with plenty of room to cut. Give students one sheet of paper (see sample) and cut along the lines as shown. Younger children may benefit from having this completed for them. Also offer students one strip per word family you are using. (Three are shown below but more or fewer can be accommodated based on your students.) Have students write letters appropriate to the word families on each strip using three fingers between each for spacing. Sample strips are provided and can be copied if needed.
	Demonstrate how to thread the strip through the cuts with the letters showing on top. (See sample)
	Allow students to thread the strip into the slats that have been cut and read each word as the strip is pulled through. Remind students that each of the words in the family rhyme. After each student reads a few words, move on to the next. If a student is struggling offer help in sounding out the initial sound and ending, with a reminder that only the initial sound is changing. Struggling students may benefit from watching the first strip being read on an overhead.
Closing
Once all students have had a chance to read a few rhyming words, have students choose at least two words from a single family and draw pictures to illustrate that rhyming word pair.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Story Themes 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Pre-Reading and making predictions: Look through the cover, illustrations, title, table of contents etc. Talk about the idea of a club and brainstorm ideas of clubs students are in, or know about or want to make. (CFU: Listen and write different types of clubs as students tell you. Continuously challenge and ask follow-up questions as you add to the board bubble map.)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Read The Only One Club aloud to the class. (CFU: Check for understanding after every idea or step, continuously ask to clarify vocabulary or repeat words throughout reading.)
Guided Practice 1
Teach descriptive qualities and character traits by writing traits about myself on the board. Ask students what I am doing and aid them to the answer of “describing myself” or “writing traits about me. Have students read the listed descriptions and decide as a class which ones make me ‘unique’ and eligible for ‘the only one club.’ (CFU: continuously aid students to the correct answers, while challenging them to think further and more in depth about each description I have written about myself.)
Guided Practice 2
Review the simple idea of uniqueness. “I’m the only one wearing heels… so that makes me unique! I am the only one who has lived in Czech Republic… so that also makes me unique!” Give students a small piece of paper, and have them create a sentence about themselves to describe their uniqueness. Then have students write one thing about themselves they feel is different from others in the class. Have the students crumple it up, stand in a large circle around the classroom and have student throw it to the center box I placed. (CFU: rotate around the class as I answer questions, help students brainstorm ideas, or assist in writing their sentence.)
Independent Practice
Have students go to the center of the classroom and choose a ‘snowball’ of crumpled paper.  Then have students work independently and create a badge for their classmates with what was written on their chosen ‘snowball.’
Closing
Choose students at random to present their badges, and either have students guess who it belongs to, or simple have students stand and accept their new badge when it is presented by their classmate.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Tearing Into Vocabulary 2</pattern>
    <template>
Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>What is a Verb 2</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class to sing the birthday song.
	Encourage them to talk about how they celebrate their birthday.
	This should be an introduction to tell about action words or Verbs. The purpose is not just to introduce Verbs but to help the children understand that birthdays are special days so we celebrate the days that someone is born.
Body of Lesson
	Remind students that verbs are action words.
	Show the students the procedure of how to wrap a gift using different verbs. Students should be wrapping a box at their desk as teacher models.
	Next, have each student switch wrapped boxes with a partner. All must be able to have a box.
	Now ask them to imagine what they wish is inside their wrapped box. What can it do for them?
	Request them to make sentences that use verbs to tell how the gift they imagine can be useful for them.
	Do the optional activity if desired. (Modification and Differentiation)
Closing
	As a class, discuss many of the verbs that were used in the activity today. Write verbs on the board or on to chart paper.
	Ask them what will they do on their next birthday.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Main Idea 2</pattern>
    <template>
        
Opening to Lesson
The teacher will read a short passage. Next, the teacher will ask for volunteers to share with the class what they think the passage was about, while writing the main ideas on the board.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will review the main ideas summarized on the board. The teacher will ask the students if these are copied from the passage or if they are their own words. The teacher will highlight the difference between identifying the main idea and supporting details, as they did yesterday, and summarizing the expository text in their own words, based on these ideas identified. The teacher will allow for students to ask questions and then explain to the class that they will be summarizing main ideas and supporting details today.
Independent Practice
The teacher will create cooperative groups, different from the previous day, and provide the students with an article from a children’s magazine. The teacher will ask the students to use the main ideas chart provided to write the main idea and supporting details on their paper. The teacher will ask the group to discuss the article and write a summary of the expository text on a large sheet of poster paper provided, using the main idea and supporting details.
Closing
The teacher will choose one group at a time to present their summary and poster to the class. After each group presents the text’s main idea and supporting details in their own words. The teacher will close by explaining the importance of this unit, “It is important to identify the main idea and supporting details because: it will help you understand the most important information in an expository text and other types of passages. It will also help you to take tests and even help you to support your own ideas when writing on your own.”

    </template>
</category>
<!-- STANDARD 2 ENDS-->
<!-- STANDARD 3 STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>STANDARD 3 LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        3rd Grade English Language Lesson Plans
        *Authors Purpose 3
        *Collaborative Questioning 3
        *Discovering Adjectives 3
        *Fable Lesson 3
        *Hiding Homophones 3
        *Main Idea 3
        *Main Idea and Details 3
        *Moody Reading 3
        *Short Stories 3
        *Story Themes 3
        *Tearing Into Vocabulary 3
        *Web of Ideas 3
        *What is a Verb 3
        *Writing Main Idea 3
        *Writing Narratives 3
        *Writing to a Photograph 3
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Authors Purpose 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will gain students' attention by playing a familiar/popular song (age appropriate).
	Teacher can ask students to listen to the lyrics.
	Students will then talk in groups to try to figure out the meaning/main idea of the song.
Body of Lesson
	As a class, read “Frog and Toad are Friends” by Arnold Lobel.
	In a circle on the rug,  review the meaning of “author’s message”.
	Students will brainstorm with the person next to them in order to create an answer to the following question: “Why do you think we need to spend time thinking about the author’s purpose?”
	Students will share their responses.
Guided/Independent Practice
	Students will work in groups to fill out the graphic organizer chart.
	Why did the author write this story?How do you know?
	Each group will present their findings to the rest of the class.
Closing
	Each student will receive one post-it.
	On the post-it, students will work independently to answer the following question: “Why do you think it is important to think about the author’s purpose?”
	At the end of the lesson, students will stick their post-its to the board or a pre-made chart. The chart can simply be made from butcher paper.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Collaborative Questioning 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will ask the students what they have been discussing at recess together.
	For example, baseball, a popular singer, a scandal at school, etc…
	Ask students to briefly describe what it is like when they discuss something with their friends.
	Post a copy of the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet for students to see.
	Explain that in every day discussions, you ask questions based on a variety of levels of critical thinking.
	For example: What is the name of the Giant’s pitcher (Level 1)? Are the Giant’s going to win the World Series again (Level 3)? What are some obstacles they may have (Level 2/3)? What is your opinion (Level 3)?
	Explain that we are going to generate and answer questions to generate one-on-one discussions about a topic in class.
Body of Lesson
	The teacher will select a text. The text should be standards based in Science or History. It could be from the text book.
Students can read the text in pairs or aloud as a class.
 
 Have the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet posted for reference.
	Explain to the students that when we discuss something, there are various levels of discussion, and that the discussion begins with questions.
	Explain that In Level 1 questions, you simply need to identify an answer.	For example: How many hours does it take for the earth to make a full rotation?
	Showing the chart, explain that in level 2 questions, you need to explain and analyze facts. For example: Why does Earth rotate at a different speed than Jupiter?•	Explain that in Level 3 questions, you can evaluate facts or make opinions based on facts: Do you believe it would be better to live on a planet that spins at a different speed?
	Give students about 10 minutes to re-read the text you independently.  Instruct them to think of questions that they could ask a partner and write their questions on the worksheet according to Costa’s levels, using the guide words to create the questions.
	After 10-15 minutes, if students are struggling to come up with questions, let them work with partners to create more questions.
	Now, use a pairing method to partner students.
	Give each pair 5 minutes to answer 2 of each other’s questions and discuss the answers.
	After 5 minutes, have students partner with a new student and answer another 2 questions.
	Repeat until all questions are answered.
Closing
When students have returned to their seats ask the class who they think had the most interesting question. Use equity cards to choose a student and have them explain their favorite question (for example, would you rather live on a planet that rotated at a different speed). Lead a class discussion based on this students question.  Repeat as time allows.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Discovering Adjectives 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the students what an Adjective is and write their definition on the board. (A describing word).
	Ask students what their favorite adjectives are and make a list of as many as they can think of on the board.
	Delicious, fun, pretty, smart, happy, sad, angry, rich, red, green, blue, cold, hot, sweet….
Body of Lesson
Modeling
	The teacher shows the students a bundle of grapes and asks how many students have eaten grapes before. Probably all of the students have.
	Now ask students what adjectives listed on the board could describe the look of the grapes.
	Add words to the list as students shout them out: green, purple, round, small, oval, smooth, pretty, weird…
	Now give a few students a grape and ask them what the grape physically feels like to the touch: cold, round, wet, sticky…
	Smell the grapes and instruct students to do the same, add more adjectives to the board: fruity, sweet,…
	Now eat one of the grapes and tell the students “Mmmm, delicious, sweet, a little sour, juicy, etc…” Let some students eat the grapes and add more adjectives to the list.
	Now ask those students how they feel after eating the grapes: hungry, happy, satisfied…
	Now ask the students who didn’t participate how they feel: hungry, sad…
	Give the rest of the students a grape.
Guided Practice
	Divide students into groups of 4.
	Give each student a worksheet.
	Pass out 4 identical objects to each group (1 group receives 4 apples, group 2 recieves 4 juice boxes, etc…)
	Instruct students to wait for your instructions as they work in their groups.
	In groups, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Look.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Touch.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Smell.
		Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Taste.
	Finally, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Feel (emotional)
	Depending on time, you can give students an additional worksheet and repeat the assignment with another food object.
Independent Practice
	As independent practice, students will write a summary of the days activity, using their favorite adjectives.
	Ex. Today in class I worked with my group to describe an apple. First, we just looked at the apple, it was round, red and inviting. Next, we touched the cool, smooth apple and thought of more adjectives to describe it. Then, we ate the apple. It was delicious, juicy and sweet. Finally we described how eating the apple made me feel. It made me feel happy and satisfied, but also ready for lunch! All in all, it was a fantastic activity.
Closing
Have students read their summaries aloud. Encourage students to repeat the activity at home with their family, commenting on the colors and tastes of their dinner.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Fable Lesson 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
To begin this lesson, explain to the students that they are going to be learning about fables. Fables originated long ago and were a form of oral storytelling.
To help students understand what oral storytelling is all about, play the Telephone Game. (Students sit in a circle. The teacher whispers one line into the ear of the student to her right. Each student will turn and repeat the line to the next person by whispering it in their ear. Once the last student hears the line, they say it out loud.) (CFU: Discuss: How did the story change? Why did the story change?)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Explain why it was so important for oral storytellers to write their tales down. “There was a man by the name of Aesop, and he wrote many of the fables that we know today. We are going to be reading two of his fables, but before we do that, let us look at what characteristics are common to most fables." Create an anchor chart on the board to review the characteristics of fables with the class. The students will then get their own copy for future guidance.
Guided Practice 1
Give each student a copy of the fable "The Town Mouse and The Country Mouse." I will read this fable aloud to the class. (CFU: Once the teacher has finished reading the story, the teacher will call on individual students and have them identify the elements of a fable found in this story, referring to the anchor chart and handout.)
Guided Practice 2
I will give each student a copy of the second fable, "The Owl and The Grasshopper." Students will read alone or in groups.
Independent Practice
Once students have finished reading, the students will share with their shoulder partner, the elements of a fable found in this story. (CFU: can monitor the student discussions at this time by walking around the room.)
Closing
Have students take turns going to the board and filing out the Venn Diagram to compare the elements of the two fables.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Hiding Homophones 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Offer students the following bit of information: English is one of the hardest languages in the world to learn. Ask students if they can guess why it is so hard. Encourage answers by displaying the following sentences: They’re going to their car that is over there.; He blew the blue horn two too many times.;  The flower made out of flour and water won number one in the contest. Explain that the words that sound the same are homophones and such words make English very difficult to learn, but that today you are going to create a ‘cheat sheet’ for some common homophones.
Body of Lesson
	Before providing a list of homophones, have students see if they can come up with some on their own. List these on the board or overhead. If there are no suggestions choose words appropriate for the grade level and ability level of the students.
	Review words and meanings with students before passing out paper. Fold the paper into fourths as shown below. Cut tabs on either side (shown below) to create flaps for each homophone pair. Have students list the pairs on the outside of the flap, across from each other. Under each flap draw a simple picture to illustrate the word. This is now a ‘cheat sheet’ for homophones. You can allow students to choose a set number of pairs or give them the words you feel are best. If time permits allow students to decorate the back.
Closing
Have students share their illustrations with a partner and then allow a few students to share which pair of homophones is the hardest for them to remember. Use the foldable in other assignments as a ‘cheat sheet’ when possible.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Main Idea 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will activate prior knowledge and connect the content to the students by asking, “what are things you do at recess?” As students brainstorm ideas aloud, the teacher will write their answers into a large bubble map outlined on the board.
The teacher will connect this content to the new information they will learn today by explaining, “Students, you’ve just listed many details that support our topic “Things we do at recess.” A topic is used to create a sentence that tells what a paragraph is about. We call this sentence the main idea. Today, we will identify main ideas and supporting details.”
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will promote the concept development by explicitly stating “the main idea is the one idea that the passage is mostly about. A supporting detail explains, or tells more about, the main idea.”
Guided Practice 1
The teacher will then show a short 1 minute video on a computer, tablet or television that uses singing and rhyming to explain examples of the main idea and supporting details in a creative way. The teacher will ask the students questions about the story in the video. “What was the main idea, what was a detail that supported the main idea?” The teacher will then provide the students with a printed copy of the lyrics. The teacher will ask the class to read the short rhyming lyrics together as a class. The teacher will play the video one more time, asking the students to sing along.
Independent Practice
The teacher will give each student one worksheet of 6 different variations. The teacher will promote skill development by asking the students to silently read the passage, to circle the main idea and underline the supporting details of the passage.
Closing
The teacher will ask select students to state their answers following the prompt: “The main idea is …” and “One supporting detail is…”

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Main Idea and Details 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Have students close their eyes and use their ears to listen to these sounds. Think about what these sounds are, what’s making them, or who is making them. “Don’t answer out loud, you will share with your partner in a second”
	Play bee sounds then think-pair-share with your partner, “I think these sounds are made by...” Call on students to answer. Sentence frame: “my partner/friend said..”
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Using the projector to show the book to all the students.
Show book to students, do a PICTURE WALK with them through the book. Ask students to predict what they think the book will be about. Read the first two pages of the book, stop and ask question to students, “Has your prediction changed? what do you predict we will learn about the main character?”
Guided Practice 1
Call up helpers to use pointer to allow students to follow along with the words as students continue to read the story. Pause to ask questions to the students and have answers prewritten but covered on graphic organizer:
What is the setting of the story?
what insects make honey?
Where do bees get the nectar that they bring back to their houses/hives?
What does the honey from Fred’s bee’s taste like?
Guided Practice 2
After the book is read, one student will come up to the front of the class and sit in the “HOT SEAT”; this student will take on the personality traits of one of the characters in the story (The bees, or Fred) and other students will take turns asking the HOT SEAT student questions pertaining to the books. The teacher will start with an example: “Mr. Bee, where do you live?” Student will respond as if he was the bee from the book. The student in HOT SEAT will then call on other students that are raising their hands to ask him/her questions.
Independent Practice
Evidence based writing: have students write their answer to the question: “Why does Fred make honey?” and support your answer with evidence from the story. Students will write 1-paragraph f students have time, they may draw a picture to represent what they wrote. (If students have time, they may draw a picture to represent what they wrote.)
Closing
Have students share their answers orally; review writing samples that are turned in.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Moody Reading 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Begin by telling students you are going to read them the same page of a book twice.
	Ask them to quietly listen as you read the same thing and then tell them you would like to discuss the readings.
	The first time you read the page (text of your choice), read in a monotone voice with no feeling at all.
	Reread the passage with emotion and feeling. Ask students what was different about the two readings.
	If students do not respond of hear the difference, guide the discussion to how reading with emotion and feeling can make a passage more interesting and hold the listeners attention.
Body of Lesson
	Tell students that they are going to practice reading with emotion. Remind them that the words are not what is important, it is the emotion they are reading with at the time. Hand out one colored strip or paper to each student; make sure a variety is handed out.
	On the board or overhead white each color that was handed out and assign it an emotion. (Samples shown) Demonstrate how to read the following line in each emotion (or your chosen emotions) “The dog jumped over the fence”.
	Allow students to take turns reading in their given ‘emotion’. The goal is not to read the words as you would if you were simply trying to understand the story, but to express an emotion while reading to understand how much more interesting this can make reading.
	*If students enjoy this activity and you want a challenge, use the colors to represent a group of people so students would read as a teacher/motivational speaker/wrestler/coach/etc. This is fun and a bit more challenging.
Closing
After everyone has had a chance to read, allow students to break into small groups of three or four. Have students choose two colors each and read through an entire text, taking turns reading in their ‘emotion’. Encourage students to read with appropriate emotions during other activities.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Short Stories 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students give ideas and participate accordingly, as I fill out the blank K-W-L organizer as a whole class, using large chart paper.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Slide show of period pictures by Dorthea Lange. Introduce the background of the assignment given to Lange to photograph this period of American History. (CFU: Ask questions of students and have discussion of how the pictures make them feel. 
Guided Practice 1
Instruction: Students will be asked to write a short story based upon one of the photographs taken by Dorthea Lange. Students will be asked to imagine themselves as the subject in the photo or ask to give life to the subject of the photo that they have picked. Students will also be able to combine the images to create a scenario based upon the hardships of the people of this period.
Independent Practice
Students will be completing assignment of a short story based upon the feelings derived of one of Dorthea Lange’s photograph of migrant workers in California.
Closing
Hold a discussion on what was learned during the lesson. Any lingering questions? Clear up misconceptions. Students will be instructed to finish this assignment at home if not finished already.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Story Themes 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Pre-Reading and making predictions: Look through the cover, illustrations, title, table of contents etc. Talk about the idea of a club and brainstorm ideas of clubs students are in, or know about or want to make. (CFU: Listen and write different types of clubs as students tell you. Continuously challenge and ask follow-up questions as you add to the board bubble map.)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Read The Only One Club aloud to the class. (CFU: Check for understanding after every idea or step, continuously ask to clarify vocabulary or repeat words throughout reading.)
Guided Practice 1
Teach descriptive qualities and character traits by writing traits about myself on the board. Ask students what I am doing and aid them to the answer of “describing myself” or “writing traits about me. Have students read the listed descriptions and decide as a class which ones make me ‘unique’ and eligible for ‘the only one club.’ (CFU: continuously aid students to the correct answers, while challenging them to think further and more in depth about each description I have written about myself.)
Guided Practice 2
Review the simple idea of uniqueness. “I’m the only one wearing heels… so that makes me unique! I am the only one who has lived in Czech Republic… so that also makes me unique!” Give students a small piece of paper, and have them create a sentence about themselves to describe their uniqueness. Then have students write one thing about themselves they feel is different from others in the class. Have the students crumple it up, stand in a large circle around the classroom and have student throw it to the center box I placed. (CFU: rotate around the class as I answer questions, help students brainstorm ideas, or assist in writing their sentence.)
Independent Practice
Have students go to the center of the classroom and choose a ‘snowball’ of crumpled paper.  Then have students work independently and create a badge for their classmates with what was written on their chosen ‘snowball.’
Closing
Choose students at random to present their badges, and either have students guess who it belongs to, or simple have students stand and accept their new badge when it is presented by their classmate.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Tearing Into Vocabulary 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
*This activity can be used with vocabulary from any subject area.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Web of Ideas 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin by asking students how they know what words to use to describe someone. Do you use what you can see? What they do? How they behave in different settings? Have students offer examples of how they would know someone is good, kind, angry, talkative, etc.
Body of Lesson
Have students read the short novel ‘Charlotte’s Web’ by E.B. White. This can be done in groups, as a class, or as individuals based on teacher preference. Tell students that throughout the book each character is demonstrating traits in different ways.
Closing
Have students fold a sheet of paper in half. On each half, front and back draw a web. In the center of the web draw one of the characters (Charlotte, Fern, Wilbur, Templeton). On each line of the web write a characteristic and find a sentence from the book that shows this characteristic. (Sample web included) Display webs.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>What is a Verb 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the class to sing the birthday song.
	Encourage them to talk about how they celebrate their birthday.
	This should be an introduction to tell about action words or Verbs. The purpose is not just to introduce Verbs but to help the children understand that birthdays are special days so we celebrate the days that someone is born.
Body of Lesson
	Remind students that verbs are action words.
	Show the students the procedure of how to wrap a gift using different verbs. Students should be wrapping a box at their desk as teacher models.
	Next, have each student switch wrapped boxes with a partner. All must be able to have a box.
	Now ask them to imagine what they wish is inside their wrapped box. What can it do for them?
	Request them to make sentences that use verbs to tell how the gift they imagine can be useful for them.
	Do the optional activity if desired. (Modification and Differentiation)
Closing
	As a class, discuss many of the verbs that were used in the activity today. Write verbs on the board or on to chart paper.
	Ask them what will they do on their next birthday.
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Main Idea 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will read a short passage. Next, the teacher will ask for volunteers to share with the class what they think the passage was about, while writing the main ideas on the board.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will review the main ideas summarized on the board. The teacher will ask the students if these are copied from the passage or if they are their own words. The teacher will highlight the difference between identifying the main idea and supporting details, as they did yesterday, and summarizing the expository text in their own words, based on these ideas identified. The teacher will allow for students to ask questions and then explain to the class that they will be summarizing main ideas and supporting details today.
Independent Practice
The teacher will create cooperative groups, different from the previous day, and provide the students with an article from a children’s magazine. The teacher will ask the students to use the main ideas chart provided to write the main idea and supporting details on their paper. The teacher will ask the group to discuss the article and write a summary of the expository text on a large sheet of poster paper provided, using the main idea and supporting details.
Closing
The teacher will choose one group at a time to present their summary and poster to the class. After each group presents the text’s main idea and supporting details in their own words. The teacher will close by explaining the importance of this unit, “It is important to identify the main idea and supporting details because: it will help you understand the most important information in an expository text and other types of passages. It will also help you to take tests and even help you to support your own ideas when writing on your own.”

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Narratives 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students will write a fable of their own for the summative assessment. (The teacher should use a narrative graphic organizer that has already been introduced.) The teacher will review the elements of the fable and have those elements projected for all students to see.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Review your ‘Writing a Fable Rubric’ and begin the graphic organizer with the students, so they know how their writing will be assessed.
Guided Practice
Student will plan and draft their fable using the graphic organizer presented.
Independent Practice
Students will revise and edit their fable by sharing with a partner. With fable in hand, students will randomly walk around the classroom until they are cued by the teacher. Once cued, students will find a partner by slapping hands, and then students will read their fables to each other. This process can be repeated as many times or over as many days as the teacher would like.
Closing
Once students have written their first draft, as well as revises based on suggestions and comments from their peers, students will meet with the teacher. Comments and or questions to state or pose during a revision conference include any of the following: What other words can we use to describe __? What else can the author write to make that point in the story?
Where in the story can the reader see some character traits of __? What descriptions of your setting create a mood in the story? After listening to your fable being read aloud (teacher reads, student listens) what did you notice? How can the moral of the story be more evident? What does the dialogue reveal about the characters in the story? Where in the fable is there a lapse in sequence?

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing to a Photograph 3</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	The following opening could be very different depending on your class. Write these bolded words on the board, or use a copy of the graphic organizer on the overhead and fill them in as your class develops the story.
	The teacher can put a picture of a known person on the board, such as the principal, the president of the school, ect…
	Now ask the students what they think this person’s name is. Students an shout out the answer.
	Write on the board: Main character: Principal Jones (for example)
	Now ask the students where Principal Jones is.
	Write on the board: Setting: East Avenue Elementary School
	Now tell the students that he is dealing with a problem and have students guess what it is. Let them think-pair-share for ideas.
	Write on the board: Problem: A goat has snuck onto campus and is hiding in the boys bathroom, principal jones has to figure out how to get it out.
	Have the students think-pair-share what principal Jones does to take care of the situation and write the brainstorm on the board with the students help.
	Event: Principal Jones calls the goat’s owner, but he is at work and can’t come until after school.
	Event: One of the 1st graders was already in the bathroom and now he cannot get out.
	Solution: Student body president rescues the 1st grader by distracting the goat with carrots and luring the scared student out of the bathroom. Principal Jones locks the bathroom until the owner can come.
Body of Lesson
	Now teacher gives copies of photos to students, or displays the photo on the overhead. The picture provided below can be used, students can bring in pictures, or the teacher can choose another one.
	Give students a copy of the graphic organizer attached, you may wish to make it larger so they have enough room for more thoughts.
	Write the following questions on the board:
	What are the kid’s names?	
Where are they?
	What do you see in the background?
	What creative words can you think of to describe the background?
	What geography related words can you use to describe their setting?
	Where are they coming from?
	Where are they going?
Why are they alone?
	Are their parents or teacher around?
	Are they lost?
	Is the little boy crying? Why?
	What is a problem that these kids could have?
	How could they solve it?
	What problems might come up as they are trying to solve the problem?
	How do they resolve them?
	How is the original problem solved in the end?
	Lead a class discussion for the first few questions, and encourage the students to give unique answers.
	Have students work independently or in pairs to answer the rest of the questions.
	Have students complete the graphic organizer.
Closing
Once students have completed the graphic organizer with as much detail as possible, students will be ready to write a creative fictional essay based on their graphic organizer.

    </template>
</category>
<!-- STANDARD 3 ENDS-->
<!-- STANDARD 4 STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>STANDARD 4 LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
    <category>
        <pattern>Author’s Purpose 4</pattern>
        <template>
            4th Grade English Language Lesson Plans 
            *Authors Purpose 4
            *Collaborative Questioning 4
            *Discovering Adjectives 4
            *Explain Those Idioms 4
            *Fable Lesson 4
            *Hiding Homophones 4
            *Main Idea 4
            *Moody Reading 4
            *Short Stories 4
            *Tearing Into Vocabulary 4
            *Theater in Action 4
            *
            *Writing Main Idea 4
            *Writing Narratives 4
            *Writing to a Photograph 4
        </template>
    </category>
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Authors Purpose 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will gain students' attention by playing a familiar/popular song (age appropriate).
	Teacher can ask students to listen to the lyrics.
	Students will then talk in groups to try to figure out the meaning/main idea of the song.
Body of Lesson
	As a class, read “Frog and Toad are Friends” by Arnold Lobel.
	In a circle on the rug,  review the meaning of “author’s message”.
	Students will brainstorm with the person next to them in order to create an answer to the following question: “Why do you think we need to spend time thinking about the author’s purpose?”
	Students will share their responses.
Guided/Independent Practice
	Students will work in groups to fill out the graphic organizer chart.
	Why did the author write this story?How do you know?
	Each group will present their findings to the rest of the class.
Closing
	Each student will receive one post-it.
	On the post-it, students will work independently to answer the following question: “Why do you think it is important to think about the author’s purpose?”
	At the end of the lesson, students will stick their post-its to the board or a pre-made chart. The chart can simply be made from butcher paper.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Collaborative Questioning 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will ask the students what they have been discussing at recess together.
	For example, baseball, a popular singer, a scandal at school, etc…
	Ask students to briefly describe what it is like when they discuss something with their friends.
	Post a copy of the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet for students to see.
	Explain that in every day discussions, you ask questions based on a variety of levels of critical thinking.
	For example: What is the name of the Giant’s pitcher (Level 1)? Are the Giant’s going to win the World Series again (Level 3)? What are some obstacles they may have (Level 2/3)? What is your opinion (Level 3)?
	Explain that we are going to generate and answer questions to generate one-on-one discussions about a topic in class.
Body of Lesson
	The teacher will select a text. The text should be standards based in Science or History. It could be from the text book.
	Students can read the text in pairs or aloud as a class.
 
	Have the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet posted for reference.
	Explain to the students that when we discuss something, there are various levels of discussion, and that the discussion begins with questions.
	Explain that In Level 1 questions, you simply need to identify an answer.
	For example: How many hours does it take for the earth to make a full rotation?
	Showing the chart, explain that in level 2 questions, you need to explain and analyze facts. For example: Why does Earth rotate at a different speed than Jupiter?
	Explain that in Level 3 questions, you can evaluate facts or make opinions based on facts: Do you believe it would be better to live on a planet that spins at a different speed?
	Give students about 10 minutes to re-read the text you independently.  Instruct them to think of questions that they could ask a partner and write their questions on the worksheet according to Costa’s levels, using the guide words to create the questions.
	After 10-15 minutes, if students are struggling to come up with questions, let them work with partners to create more questions.
	Now, use a pairing method to partner students.
	Give each pair 5 minutes to answer 2 of each other’s questions and discuss the answers.
	After 5 minutes, have students partner with a new student and answer another 2 questions.
	Repeat until all questions are answered.
Closing
When students have returned to their seats ask the class who they think had the most interesting question. Use equity cards to choose a student and have them explain their favorite question (for example, would you rather live on a planet that rotated at a different speed). Lead a class discussion based on this students question.  Repeat as time allows.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Discovering Adjectives 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Ask the students what an Adjective is and write their definition on the board. (A describing word).
	Ask students what their favorite adjectives are and make a list of as many as they can think of on the board.
	Delicious, fun, pretty, smart, happy, sad, angry, rich, red, green, blue, cold, hot, sweet….
Body of Lesson
Modeling
	The teacher shows the students a bundle of grapes and asks how many students have eaten grapes before. Probably all of the students have.
	Now ask students what adjectives listed on the board could describe the look of the grapes.
	Add words to the list as students shout them out: green, purple, round, small, oval, smooth, pretty, weird…
	Now give a few students a grape and ask them what the grape physically feels like to the touch: cold, round, wet, sticky…
	Smell the grapes and instruct students to do the same, add more adjectives to the board: fruity, sweet,…
	Now eat one of the grapes and tell the students “Mmmm, delicious, sweet, a little sour, juicy, etc…” Let some students eat the grapes and add more adjectives to the list.
	Now ask those students how they feel after eating the grapes: hungry, happy, satisfied…
	Now ask the students who didn’t participate how they feel: hungry, sad…
	Give the rest of the students a grape.
Guided Practice
	Divide students into groups of 4.
	Give each student a worksheet.
	Pass out 4 identical objects to each group (1 group receives 4 apples, group 2 recieves 4 juice boxes, etc…)
	Instruct students to wait for your instructions as they work in their groups.
	In groups, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Look.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Touch.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Smell.
	Next, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Taste.
	Finally, students will write as many adjectives as they can think of in the box that corresponds with Feel (emotional)
	Depending on time, you can give students an additional worksheet and repeat the assignment with another food object.
Independent Practice
	As independent practice, students will write a summary of the days activity, using their favorite adjectives.
	Ex. Today in class I worked with my group to describe an apple. First, we just looked at the apple, it was round, red and inviting. Next, we touched the cool, smooth apple and thought of more adjectives to describe it. Then, we ate the apple. It was delicious, juicy and sweet. Finally we described how eating the apple made me feel. It made me feel happy and satisfied, but also ready for lunch! All in all, it was a fantastic activity.
Closing
Have students read their summaries aloud. Encourage students to repeat the activity at home with their family, commenting on the colors and tastes of their dinner.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Explain Those Idioms 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by asking students if they have ever heard of an idiom. Explain that an idiom is a common word or phrase that has a cultural as well as actual meaning. Share the phrase ‘kick the bucket’ and explain as above. Explain that sometimes it is easiest to show the different meanings in drawing form, which is what they will do today.
Body of Lesson
Hand out long sheets of paper to each student. Have students fold the paper lengthwise in half and then in half twice width wise (sample below). Have students choose four idioms they would like to illustrate from the list (samples given). If needed, explain some of the idioms to students. In each box have students draw a real meaning illustration and a perceived meaning illustration for each  idiom.
Closing
Review each idiom with students in relation to their drawing. Display drawings. 
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Fable Lesson 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
To begin this lesson, explain to the students that they are going to be learning about fables. Fables originated long ago and were a form of oral storytelling.
To help students understand what oral storytelling is all about, play the Telephone Game. (Students sit in a circle. The teacher whispers one line into the ear of the student to her right. Each student will turn and repeat the line to the next person by whispering it in their ear. Once the last student hears the line, they say it out loud.) (CFU: Discuss: How did the story change? Why did the story change?)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Explain why it was so important for oral storytellers to write their tales down. “There was a man by the name of Aesop, and he wrote many of the fables that we know today. We are going to be reading two of his fables, but before we do that, let us look at what characteristics are common to most fables." Create an anchor chart on the board to review the characteristics of fables with the class. The students will then get their own copy for future guidance.
Guided Practice 1
Give each student a copy of the fable "The Town Mouse and The Country Mouse." I will read this fable aloud to the class. (CFU: Once the teacher has finished reading the story, the teacher will call on individual students and have them identify the elements of a fable found in this story, referring to the anchor chart and handout.)
Guided Practice 2
I will give each student a copy of the second fable, "The Owl and The Grasshopper." Students will read alone or in groups.
Independent Practice
Once students have finished reading, the students will share with their shoulder partner, the elements of a fable found in this story. (CFU: can monitor the student discussions at this time by walking around the room.)
Closing
Have students take turns going to the board and filing out the Venn Diagram to compare the elements of the two fables.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Hiding Homophones 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Offer students the following bit of information: English is one of the hardest languages in the world to learn. Ask students if they can guess why it is so hard. Encourage answers by displaying the following sentences: They’re going to their car that is over there.; He blew the blue horn two too many times.;  The flower made out of flour and water won number one in the contest. Explain that the words that sound the same are homophones and such words make English very difficult to learn, but that today you are going to create a ‘cheat sheet’ for some common homophones.
Body of Lesson
	Before providing a list of homophones, have students see if they can come up with some on their own. List these on the board or overhead. If there are no suggestions choose words appropriate for the grade level and ability level of the students.
	Review words and meanings with students before passing out paper. Fold the paper into fourths as shown below. Cut tabs on either side (shown below) to create flaps for each homophone pair. Have students list the pairs on the outside of the flap, across from each other. Under each flap draw a simple picture to illustrate the word. This is now a ‘cheat sheet’ for homophones. You can allow students to choose a set number of pairs or give them the words you feel are best. If time permits allow students to decorate the back.
Closing
Have students share their illustrations with a partner and then allow a few students to share which pair of homophones is the hardest for them to remember. Use the foldable in other assignments as a ‘cheat sheet’ when possible.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Main Idea 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will activate prior knowledge and connect the content to the students by asking, “what are things you do at recess?” As students brainstorm ideas aloud, the teacher will write their answers into a large bubble map outlined on the board.
The teacher will connect this content to the new information they will learn today by explaining, “Students, you’ve just listed many details that support our topic “Things we do at recess.” A topic is used to create a sentence that tells what a paragraph is about. We call this sentence the main idea. Today, we will identify main ideas and supporting details.”
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will promote the concept development by explicitly stating “the main idea is the one idea that the passage is mostly about. A supporting detail explains, or tells more about, the main idea.”
Guided Practice 1
The teacher will then show a short 1 minute video on a computer, tablet or television that uses singing and rhyming to explain examples of the main idea and supporting details in a creative way. The teacher will ask the students questions about the story in the video. “What was the main idea, what was a detail that supported the main idea?” The teacher will then provide the students with a printed copy of the lyrics. The teacher will ask the class to read the short rhyming lyrics together as a class. The teacher will play the video one more time, asking the students to sing along.
Independent Practice
The teacher will give each student one worksheet of 6 different variations. The teacher will promote skill development by asking the students to silently read the passage, to circle the main idea and underline the supporting details of the passage.
Closing
The teacher will ask select students to state their answers following the prompt: “The main idea is …” and “One supporting detail is…”


    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Moody Reading 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Begin by telling students you are going to read them the same page of a book twice.
	Ask them to quietly listen as you read the same thing and then tell them you would like to discuss the readings.
	The first time you read the page (text of your choice), read in a monotone voice with no feeling at all.
	Reread the passage with emotion and feeling. Ask students what was different about the two readings.
	If students do not respond of hear the difference, guide the discussion to how reading with emotion and feeling can make a passage more interesting and hold the listeners attention.
Body of Lesson
	Tell students that they are going to practice reading with emotion. Remind them that the words are not what is important, it is the emotion they are reading with at the time. Hand out one colored strip or paper to each student; make sure a variety is handed out.
	On the board or overhead white each color that was handed out and assign it an emotion. (Samples shown) Demonstrate how to read the following line in each emotion (or your chosen emotions) “The dog jumped over the fence”.
	Allow students to take turns reading in their given ‘emotion’. The goal is not to read the words as you would if you were simply trying to understand the story, but to express an emotion while reading to understand how much more interesting this can make reading.
	*If students enjoy this activity and you want a challenge, use the colors to represent a group of people so students would read as a teacher/motivational speaker/wrestler/coach/etc. This is fun and a bit more challenging.
Closing
After everyone has had a chance to read, allow students to break into small groups of three or four. Have students choose two colors each and read through an entire text, taking turns reading in their ‘emotion’. Encourage students to read with appropriate emotions during other activities.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Short Stories 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students give ideas and participate accordingly, as I fill out the blank K-W-L organizer as a whole class, using large chart paper.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Slide show of period pictures by Dorthea Lange. Introduce the background of the assignment given to Lange to photograph this period of American History. (CFU: Ask questions of students and have discussion of how the pictures make them feel. 
Guided Practice 1
Instruction: Students will be asked to write a short story based upon one of the photographs taken by Dorthea Lange. Students will be asked to imagine themselves as the subject in the photo or ask to give life to the subject of the photo that they have picked. Students will also be able to combine the images to create a scenario based upon the hardships of the people of this period.
Independent Practice
Students will be completing assignment of a short story based upon the feelings derived of one of Dorthea Lange’s photograph of migrant workers in California.
Closing
Hold a discussion on what was learned during the lesson. Any lingering questions? Clear up misconceptions. Students will be instructed to finish this assignment at home if not finished already.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Tearing Into Vocabulary 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
*This activity can be used with vocabulary from any subject area.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Theater in Action 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Watch a video or read a picture book of the story, Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland.
	Read, as a class, the summary of the story, Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland.
Body of Lesson
	Explain to the students that they will be recreating the story of Alice in Wonderland, but that each group will create one scene, and then the class will perform the entire play.
	Tell the students that they can have creativity in the scene, it does not need to be exactly like it is in a movie they’ve seen or in the summary they are given, they should be creative with their writing and make it interesting.
	For example, each scene is relatively short and may only have 2 characters. The students can create more roles by having 2 Alices, or 2 caterpillars, etc…
	Teacher will divide students into groups of 4 or 5 and give them a slip of paper with a scene from the story.
	Post the list of directions on the board for students to follow. Students work in groups to complete these tasks.
	Read the summary aloud in your group.
	Discuss how the scene is portrayed in the video or in another movie you have seen.
	How many characters are there in the scene?
	Each student in your group needs to have a speaking role. What characters can you double or add so that there are enough roles for each student? (A narrator can be used).
	Discuss how you will make this an interesting scene.
	Write a script that includes dialogue for each character.
	Practice acting out the scene.
	Be prepared to perform!
	The teacher should monitor groups closely and help them if they are having writer’s block.
	When all students have developed their scene, they class performs the final product!
Closing
Students can write a summary of the play as performed by the class. Surely it will be quite different than the original story!

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Web of Ideas 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin by asking students how they know what words to use to describe someone. Do you use what you can see? What they do? How they behave in different settings? Have students offer examples of how they would know someone is good, kind, angry, talkative, etc.
Body of Lesson
Have students read the short novel ‘Charlotte’s Web’ by E.B. White. This can be done in groups, as a class, or as individuals based on teacher preference. Tell students that throughout the book each character is demonstrating traits in different ways.
Closing
Have students fold a sheet of paper in half. On each half, front and back draw a web. In the center of the web draw one of the characters (Charlotte, Fern, Wilbur, Templeton). On each line of the web write a characteristic and find a sentence from the book that shows this characteristic. (Sample web included) Display webs.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Main Idea 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
The teacher will read a short passage. Next, the teacher will ask for volunteers to share with the class what they think the passage was about, while writing the main ideas on the board.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
The teacher will review the main ideas summarized on the board. The teacher will ask the students if these are copied from the passage or if they are their own words. The teacher will highlight the difference between identifying the main idea and supporting details, as they did yesterday, and summarizing the expository text in their own words, based on these ideas identified. The teacher will allow for students to ask questions and then explain to the class that they will be summarizing main ideas and supporting details today.
Independent Practice
The teacher will create cooperative groups, different from the previous day, and provide the students with an article from a children’s magazine. The teacher will ask the students to use the main ideas chart provided to write the main idea and supporting details on their paper. The teacher will ask the group to discuss the article and write a summary of the expository text on a large sheet of poster paper provided, using the main idea and supporting details.
Closing
The teacher will choose one group at a time to present their summary and poster to the class. After each group presents the text’s main idea and supporting details in their own words. The teacher will close by explaining the importance of this unit, “It is important to identify the main idea and supporting details because: it will help you understand the most important information in an expository text and other types of passages. It will also help you to take tests and even help you to support your own ideas when writing on your own.”

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Narratives 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students will write a fable of their own for the summative assessment. (The teacher should use a narrative graphic organizer that has already been introduced.) The teacher will review the elements of the fable and have those elements projected for all students to see.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Review your ‘Writing a Fable Rubric’ and begin the graphic organizer with the students, so they know how their writing will be assessed.
Guided Practice
Student will plan and draft their fable using the graphic organizer presented.
Independent Practice
Students will revise and edit their fable by sharing with a partner. With fable in hand, students will randomly walk around the classroom until they are cued by the teacher. Once cued, students will find a partner by slapping hands, and then students will read their fables to each other. This process can be repeated as many times or over as many days as the teacher would like.
Closing
Once students have written their first draft, as well as revises based on suggestions and comments from their peers, students will meet with the teacher. Comments and or questions to state or pose during a revision conference include any of the following: What other words can we use to describe __? What else can the author write to make that point in the story?
Where in the story can the reader see some character traits of __? What descriptions of your setting create a mood in the story? After listening to your fable being read aloud (teacher reads, student listens) what did you notice? How can the moral of the story be more evident? What does the dialogue reveal about the characters in the story? Where in the fable is there a lapse in sequence?

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing to a Photograph 4</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	The following opening could be very different depending on your class. Write these bolded words on the board, or use a copy of the graphic organizer on the overhead and fill them in as your class develops the story.
	The teacher can put a picture of a known person on the board, such as the principal, the president of the school, ect…
	Now ask the students what they think this person’s name is. Students an shout out the answer.
	Write on the board: Main character: Principal Jones (for example)
	Now ask the students where Principal Jones is.
Write on the board: Setting: East Avenue Elementary School
	Now tell the students that he is dealing with a problem and have students guess what it is. Let them think-pair-share for ideas.
	Write on the board: Problem: A goat has snuck onto campus and is hiding in the boys bathroom, principal jones has to figure out how to get it out.
	Have the students think-pair-share what principal Jones does to take care of the situation and write the brainstorm on the board with the students help.
	Event: Principal Jones calls the goat’s owner, but he is at work and can’t come until after school.
	Event: One of the 1st graders was already in the bathroom and now he cannot get out.
	Solution: Student body president rescues the 1st grader by distracting the goat with carrots and luring the scared student out of the bathroom. Principal Jones locks the bathroom until the owner can come.
Body of Lesson
	Now teacher gives copies of photos to students, or displays the photo on the overhead. The picture provided below can be used, students can bring in pictures, or the teacher can choose another one.
	Give students a copy of the graphic organizer attached, you may wish to make it larger so they have enough room for more thoughts.
	Write the following questions on the board:
	What are the kid’s names?
	Where are they?
	What do you see in the background?
	What creative words can you think of to describe the background?
	What geography related words can you use to describe their setting?
	Where are they coming from?
	Where are they going?
	Why are they alone?
	Are their parents or teacher around?
	Are they lost?
	Is the little boy crying? Why?
	What is a problem that these kids could have?
	How could they solve it?
What problems might come up as they are trying to solve the problem?
	How do they resolve them?
	How is the original problem solved in the end?
	Lead a class discussion for the first few questions, and encourage the students to give unique answers.
	Have students work independently or in pairs to answer the rest of the questions.
	Have students complete the graphic organizer.
Closing
Once students have completed the graphic organizer with as much detail as possible, students will be ready to write a creative fictional essay based on their graphic organizer.

    </template>
</category>
<!-- STANDARD 4 ENDS-->
<!-- STANDARD 5 STARTS -->
<category>
    <pattern>STANDARD 5 LESSON PLAN</pattern>
    <template>
        5th Grade English Language Lesson Plans
        *Collaborative Questioning 5
        *Explain Those Idioms 5
        *Fable Lesson 5
        *Hiding Homophones 5
        *Moody Reading 5
        *Parts of Speech BINGO 5
        *Short Stories 5
        *Tearing Into Vocabulary 5
        *Theater in Action 5
        *Web of Ideas 5
        *Writing Narratives 5
        *Writing to a Photograph 5
    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Collaborative Questioning 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Teacher will ask the students what they have been discussing at recess together.
	For example, baseball, a popular singer, a scandal at school, etc…
	Ask students to briefly describe what it is like when they discuss something with their friends.
	Post a copy of the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet for students to see.
	Explain that in every day discussions, you ask questions based on a variety of levels of critical thinking.
	For example: What is the name of the Giant’s pitcher (Level 1)? Are the Giant’s going to win the World Series again (Level 3)? What are some obstacles they may have (Level 2/3)? What is your opinion (Level 3)?
	Explain that we are going to generate and answer questions to generate one-on-one discussions about a topic in class.
Body of Lesson
	The teacher will select a text. The text should be standards based in Science or History. It could be from the text book.
	Students can read the text in pairs or aloud as a class.
 
	Have the “Critical Thinking: Levels of Questioning” worksheet posted for reference.
	Explain to the students that when we discuss something, there are various levels of discussion, and that the discussion begins with questions.
	Explain that In Level 1 questions, you simply need to identify an answer.
	For example: How many hours does it take for the earth to make a full rotation?
	Showing the chart, explain that in level 2 questions, you need to explain and analyze facts. For example: Why does Earth rotate at a different speed than Jupiter?
	Explain that in Level 3 questions, you can evaluate facts or make opinions based on facts: Do you believe it would be better to live on a planet that spins at a different speed?
	Give students about 10 minutes to re-read the text you independently.  Instruct them to think of questions that they could ask a partner and write their questions on the worksheet according to Costa’s levels, using the guide words to create the questions.
	After 10-15 minutes, if students are struggling to come up with questions, let them work with partners to create more questions.
	Now, use a pairing method to partner students.
	Give each pair 5 minutes to answer 2 of each other’s questions and discuss the answers.
	After 5 minutes, have students partner with a new student and answer another 2 questions.
	Repeat until all questions are answered.
Closing
When students have returned to their seats ask the class who they think had the most interesting question. Use equity cards to choose a student and have them explain their favorite question (for example, would you rather live on a planet that rotated at a different speed). Lead a class discussion based on this students question.  Repeat as time allows.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Explain Those Idioms 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by asking students if they have ever heard of an idiom. Explain that an idiom is a common word or phrase that has a cultural as well as actual meaning. Share the phrase ‘kick the bucket’ and explain as above. Explain that sometimes it is easiest to show the different meanings in drawing form, which is what they will do today.
Body of Lesson
Hand out long sheets of paper to each student. Have students fold the paper lengthwise in half and then in half twice width wise (sample below). Have students choose four idioms they would like to illustrate from the list (samples given). If needed, explain some of the idioms to students. In each box have students draw a real meaning illustration and a perceived meaning illustration for each  idiom.
Closing
Review each idiom with students in relation to their drawing. Display drawings.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Fable Lesson 5</pattern>
    <template>Opening to Lesson
To begin this lesson, explain to the students that they are going to be learning about fables. Fables originated long ago and were a form of oral storytelling.
To help students understand what oral storytelling is all about, play the Telephone Game. (Students sit in a circle. The teacher whispers one line into the ear of the student to her right. Each student will turn and repeat the line to the next person by whispering it in their ear. Once the last student hears the line, they say it out loud.) (CFU: Discuss: How did the story change? Why did the story change?)
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Explain why it was so important for oral storytellers to write their tales down. “There was a man by the name of Aesop, and he wrote many of the fables that we know today. We are going to be reading two of his fables, but before we do that, let us look at what characteristics are common to most fables." Create an anchor chart on the board to review the characteristics of fables with the class. The students will then get their own copy for future guidance.
Guided Practice 1
Give each student a copy of the fable "The Town Mouse and The Country Mouse." I will read this fable aloud to the class. (CFU: Once the teacher has finished reading the story, the teacher will call on individual students and have them identify the elements of a fable found in this story, referring to the anchor chart and handout.)
Guided Practice 2
I will give each student a copy of the second fable, "The Owl and The Grasshopper." Students will read alone or in groups.
Independent Practice
Once students have finished reading, the students will share with their shoulder partner, the elements of a fable found in this story. (CFU: can monitor the student discussions at this time by walking around the room.)
Closing
Have students take turns going to the board and filing out the Venn Diagram to compare the elements of the two fables.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Hiding Homophones 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Offer students the following bit of information: English is one of the hardest languages in the world to learn. Ask students if they can guess why it is so hard. Encourage answers by displaying the following sentences: They’re going to their car that is over there.; He blew the blue horn two too many times.;  The flower made out of flour and water won number one in the contest. Explain that the words that sound the same are homophones and such words make English very difficult to learn, but that today you are going to create a ‘cheat sheet’ for some common homophones.
Body of Lesson
	Before providing a list of homophones, have students see if they can come up with some on their own. List these on the board or overhead. If there are no suggestions choose words appropriate for the grade level and ability level of the students.
	Review words and meanings with students before passing out paper. Fold the paper into fourths as shown below. Cut tabs on either side (shown below) to create flaps for each homophone pair. Have students list the pairs on the outside of the flap, across from each other. Under each flap draw a simple picture to illustrate the word. This is now a ‘cheat sheet’ for homophones. You can allow students to choose a set number of pairs or give them the words you feel are best. If time permits allow students to decorate the back.
Closing
Have students share their illustrations with a partner and then allow a few students to share which pair of homophones is the hardest for them to remember. Use the foldable in other assignments as a ‘cheat sheet’ when possible.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Moody Reading 5</pattern>
    <template>Opening to Lesson
	Begin by telling students you are going to read them the same page of a book twice.
	Ask them to quietly listen as you read the same thing and then tell them you would like to discuss the readings.
	The first time you read the page (text of your choice), read in a monotone voice with no feeling at all.
	Reread the passage with emotion and feeling. Ask students what was different about the two readings.
	If students do not respond of hear the difference, guide the discussion to how reading with emotion and feeling can make a passage more interesting and hold the listeners attention.
Body of Lesson
	Tell students that they are going to practice reading with emotion. Remind them that the words are not what is important, it is the emotion they are reading with at the time. Hand out one colored strip or paper to each student; make sure a variety is handed out.
	On the board or overhead white each color that was handed out and assign it an emotion. (Samples shown) Demonstrate how to read the following line in each emotion (or your chosen emotions) “The dog jumped over the fence”.
	Allow students to take turns reading in their given ‘emotion’. The goal is not to read the words as you would if you were simply trying to understand the story, but to express an emotion while reading to understand how much more interesting this can make reading.
	*If students enjoy this activity and you want a challenge, use the colors to represent a group of people so students would read as a teacher/motivational speaker/wrestler/coach/etc. This is fun and a bit more challenging.
Closing
After everyone has had a chance to read, allow students to break into small groups of three or four. Have students choose two colors each and read through an entire text, taking turns reading in their ‘emotion’. Encourage students to read with appropriate emotions during other activities.
</template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Parts of Speech BINGO 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin the lesson by asking students to define Nouns: person, place, thing, or idea; Verbs : action words; Prepositions: a word that shows relation to another word; Adjective: descriptive word. Ask students for examples of each to clarify understanding.
Body of Lesson
	Give each student a BINGO card. Have students fill in each square with either (noun, verb, preposition, or adjective) The center can be a free square if desired.  All cards will be different as students decide what term is written in each square. However, each should be used at least 5 times. (Sample shown) Each student should also have a dry erase marker.
	As you read a word from your list, the student should write that word on the card next to a spot that shows a term. If you say teacher, the child should find a square that says noun and write teacher. The position cannot be changed once it is written. Continue until someone gets a BINGO.
•	Repeat as desired.
Closing
If desired review once again what each term means. In addition, it is always nice to offer extra credit or extra free time to each winner. This is a great activity to practice vocabulary or other skills while taking only a short amount of time between other planned activities.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>SS5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students give ideas and participate accordingly, as I fill out the blank K-W-L organizer as a whole class, using large chart paper.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Slide show of period pictures by Dorthea Lange. Introduce the background of the assignment given to Lange to photograph this period of American History. (CFU: Ask questions of students and have discussion of how the pictures make them feel. 
Guided Practice 1
Instruction: Students will be asked to write a short story based upon one of the photographs taken by Dorthea Lange. Students will be asked to imagine themselves as the subject in the photo or ask to give life to the subject of the photo that they have picked. Students will also be able to combine the images to create a scenario based upon the hardships of the people of this period.
Independent Practice
Students will be completing assignment of a short story based upon the feelings derived of one of Dorthea Lange’s photograph of migrant workers in California.
Closing
Hold a discussion on what was learned during the lesson. Any lingering questions? Clear up misconceptions. Students will be instructed to finish this assignment at home if not finished already.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Tearing Into Vocabulary 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Explain to students that you are going to do a quick vocabulary review that can earn them a reward/prize/etc. Explain which vocabulary you will be using for the game. Tell students that they should know or can look up the vocabulary word, but must also know a definition, a word that means the opposite of, and be able to illustrate the word.
Body of Lesson
	Begin by grouping students. Give each student in a given group a colored strip of paper (each group member should have the same color, but each group should be a different color). Tell students to fold the strip into four equal squares and then lay the paper down.
	Show students on your own paper what will be expected. Have a list of possible vocabulary words on the board. Make sure there is at least one word per student in each group or more words than students. Tell students that everyone in the group must choose a word, but no two group members can choose the same word. The chosen word will be written on the first square.
	The second square should contain a short definition of the word. Make sure all students are using a pencil to write to make the competition fair.
	The third square should contain a word that means the opposite of the vocabulary word (if this is not possible with your vocabulary then have students choose a synonym, as long as all students are doing the same thing).
	The final square should have a small, legible picture that represents the term. After all squares have been filled out, have students cut the squares apart on the fold and mix all squares from the group together.
	Have the groups exchange squares with one another. On go, the groups must work together to reassemble the strips in the right order for all the vocabulary words. Check each strip before declaring a winner.
Closing
Have the winning group read the vocabulary words and definitions that they have put together after every group finishes. If time permits, have the groups exchange again and try to put another set together.
*This activity can be used with vocabulary from any subject area.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Theater in Action 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	Watch a video or read a picture book of the story, Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland.
	Read, as a class, the summary of the story, Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland.
Body of Lesson
	Explain to the students that they will be recreating the story of Alice in Wonderland, but that each group will create one scene, and then the class will perform the entire play.
	Tell the students that they can have creativity in the scene, it does not need to be exactly like it is in a movie they’ve seen or in the summary they are given, they should be creative with their writing and make it interesting.
	For example, each scene is relatively short and may only have 2 characters. The students can create more roles by having 2 Alices, or 2 caterpillars, etc…
	Teacher will divide students into groups of 4 or 5 and give them a slip of paper with a scene from the story.
	Post the list of directions on the board for students to follow. Students work in groups to complete these tasks.
	Read the summary aloud in your group.
	Discuss how the scene is portrayed in the video or in another movie you have seen.
	How many characters are there in the scene?
	Each student in your group needs to have a speaking role. What characters can you double or add so that there are enough roles for each student? (A narrator can be used).
	Discuss how you will make this an interesting scene.
	Write a script that includes dialogue for each character.
	Practice acting out the scene.
	Be prepared to perform!
	The teacher should monitor groups closely and help them if they are having writer’s block.
	When all students have developed their scene, they class performs the final product!
Closing
Students can write a summary of the play as performed by the class. Surely it will be quite different than the original story!

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Web of Ideas 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Begin by asking students how they know what words to use to describe someone. Do you use what you can see? What they do? How they behave in different settings? Have students offer examples of how they would know someone is good, kind, angry, talkative, etc.
Body of Lesson
Have students read the short novel ‘Charlotte’s Web’ by E.B. White. This can be done in groups, as a class, or as individuals based on teacher preference. Tell students that throughout the book each character is demonstrating traits in different ways.
Closing
Have students fold a sheet of paper in half. On each half, front and back draw a web. In the center of the web draw one of the characters (Charlotte, Fern, Wilbur, Templeton). On each line of the web write a characteristic and find a sentence from the book that shows this characteristic. (Sample web included) Display webs.

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing Narratives 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
Students will write a fable of their own for the summative assessment. (The teacher should use a narrative graphic organizer that has already been introduced.) The teacher will review the elements of the fable and have those elements projected for all students to see.
Body of Lesson
Direct Teaching
Review your ‘Writing a Fable Rubric’ and begin the graphic organizer with the students, so they know how their writing will be assessed.
Guided Practice
Student will plan and draft their fable using the graphic organizer presented.
Independent Practice
Students will revise and edit their fable by sharing with a partner. With fable in hand, students will randomly walk around the classroom until they are cued by the teacher. Once cued, students will find a partner by slapping hands, and then students will read their fables to each other. This process can be repeated as many times or over as many days as the teacher would like.
Closing
Once students have written their first draft, as well as revises based on suggestions and comments from their peers, students will meet with the teacher. Comments and or questions to state or pose during a revision conference include any of the following: What other words can we use to describe __? What else can the author write to make that point in the story?
Where in the story can the reader see some character traits of __? What descriptions of your setting create a mood in the story? After listening to your fable being read aloud (teacher reads, student listens) what did you notice? How can the moral of the story be more evident? What does the dialogue reveal about the characters in the story? Where in the fable is there a lapse in sequence?

    </template>
</category>
<category>
    <pattern>Writing to a Photograph 5</pattern>
    <template>
        Opening to Lesson
	The following opening could be very different depending on your class. Write these bolded words on the board, or use a copy of the graphic organizer on the overhead and fill them in as your class develops the story.
	The teacher can put a picture of a known person on the board, such as the principal, the president of the school, ect…
	Now ask the students what they think this person’s name is. Students an shout out the answer.
	Write on the board: Main character: Principal Jones (for example)
	Now ask the students where Principal Jones is.
	Write on the board: Setting: East Avenue Elementary School
	Now tell the students that he is dealing with a problem and have students guess what it is. Let them think-pair-share for ideas.
	Write on the board: Problem: A goat has snuck onto campus and is hiding in the boys bathroom, principal jones has to figure out how to get it out.
	Have the students think-pair-share what principal Jones does to take care of the situation and write the brainstorm on the board with the students help.
	Event: Principal Jones calls the goat’s owner, but he is at work and can’t come until after school.
	Event: One of the 1st graders was already in the bathroom and now he cannot get out.
	Solution: Student body president rescues the 1st grader by distracting the goat with carrots and luring the scared student out of the bathroom. Principal Jones locks the bathroom until the owner can come.
Body of Lesson
	Now teacher gives copies of photos to students, or displays the photo on the overhead. The picture provided below can be used, students can bring in pictures, or the teacher can choose another one.
	Give students a copy of the graphic organizer attached, you may wish to make it larger so they have enough room for more thoughts.
	Write the following questions on the board:
	What are the kid’s names?
	Where are they?
	What do you see in the background?
	What creative words can you think of to describe the background?
	What geography related words can you use to describe their setting?
	Where are they coming from?
	Where are they going?
	Why are they alone?
	Are their parents or teacher around?
	Are they lost?
	Is the little boy crying? Why?
	What is a problem that these kids could have?
	How could they solve it?
	What problems might come up as they are trying to solve the problem?
	How do they resolve them?
	How is the original problem solved in the end?
	Lead a class discussion for the first few questions, and encourage the students to give unique answers.
	Have students work independently or in pairs to answer the rest of the questions.
	Have students complete the graphic organizer.
Closing
Once students have completed the graphic organizer with as much detail as possible, students will be ready to write a creative fictional essay based on their graphic organizer.

    </template>
</category>

</aiml>